Chapter 106.
Ahab's leg.
The precipitating manner in which Captain Ahad had quitted the Samuel
Enderbe of London had not been unattended with some small violence to
his own person. He had lighted with such energy upon the thwart of his boat that
his ivory leg had received a half splintering shock, and when, after
gaining his own deck, and his own pivot hole there, he so vehemently wheeled
round with an urgent command to the steersman, it was as ever something
about his not steering inflexibly enough. Then the already shaken ivory
received such an additional twist and wrench that though it still remained
entire and to all appearances lusty, yet Ahab did not deem it entirely trustworthy.
And indeed it seemed small matter for wonder that for all his pervading mad
recklessness, Ahab did at times give careful heed to the condition of that
dead bone upon which he partly stood.
For it had not been very long prior to the Peekquad's sailing from Nantucket
that he had been found one night lying prone upon the ground and insensible by
some unknown and seemingly inexplicable unimaginable casualty, his ivory limb
having been so violently displaced that it had stakewise smitten and all but
pierced his groin. Nor was it without extreme difficulty that the agonizing
wound was entirely cured.
Nor at the time had it failed to enter his monomomaniac mind that all the
anguish of that then present suffering was but the direct issue of a former
woe, and he too plainly seemed to see that as the most poisonous reptile of
the marsh perpetuates his kind, as inevitably as the sweetest songster of
the grove, so equally with every felicity, all miserable events do
naturally beget their like. Yay, more than equally, thought Ahab, since both
the ancestry and posterity of grief go further than the ancestry and posterity
of joy. Four, not to hint of this, that it is an inference from certain canonic
teachings, that while some natural enjoyments here shall have no children
born to them for the other world, but on the contrary shall be followed by the
joy childlessness of all hell's despair.
Whereas some guilty mortal miseries shall still fertily beget to themselves
an eternally progressive progeny of griefs beyond the grave. not at all to
hint of this. There still seems an inequality in the deeper analysis of the
thing. For thought Ahab, while even the highest earthly felicities have a
certain unsignifying pettiness lurking in them, but at bottom all heart woes, a
mystic significance, and in some men an archangelic grandeur, so do their
diligent tracings out not bely the obvious deduction. To trail the
genealogies of these high mortal miseries carries us at last among the
sourceless primogenitors of the gods, so that in the face of all the glad
haymaking suns and soft symboling round harvest moons, we must needs give in to
this that the gods themselves are not forever glad. The ineable sad birthark
in the brow of man is but the stamp of sorrow in the sers.
unwittingly here a secret has been divulged which perhaps might more
properly in set way have been disclosed before with many other particulars
concerning Ahab always had it remained a mystery to some why it was that for a
certain period both before and after the sailing of the Peekquad he had hidden
himself away with such grand llama-like exclusiveness and for that one interval
sought speechless refuge as it were among the marble Senate of the dead.
Captain Pel's bruted reason for this thing appeared by no means adequate,
though indeed, as touching all Ahab's deeper part, every revelation partook
more of significant darkness than of explanatory light. But in the end, it
all came out. This one matter did, at least. That dire mishap was at the
bottom of his temporary recluseness. And not only this, but to that ever
contracting dropping circle ashore, who for any reason possessed the privilege
of a less banned approach to him, to that timid circle the above hinted
casualty, remaining, as it did, moodily unaccounted for by Ahab, invested itself
with terrors not entirely underived from the land of spirits and of whales, so
that through their zeal for him they had all conspired so far as in them lay to
muffle up the knowledge of this thing from others. And hence it was that not
till a considerable interval had elapsed did it transpire upon the Peekquad's decks.
But be all this as it may, let the unseen ambiguous sinod in the air, or
the vindictive princes and potentates of fire have to do or not with earthly
Ahab. Yet in this present matter of his leg, he took plain practical procedures.
He called the carpenter, and when that functionary appeared
before him, he bad him without delay, set about making a new leg, and directed
the mates to see him supplied with all these studs and joists of jaw ivory
sperm whale, which had thus far been accumulated on the voyage, in order that
a careful selection of the stoutest, clearest grain stuff might be secured.
This done, the carpenter received orders to have the leg completed that night,
and to provide all the fittings for it, independent of those pertaining to the
distrusted one in use. Moreover, the ship's forge was ordered to be hoisted
out of its temporary idleness in the hold, and to accelerate the affair, the
blacksmith was commanded to proceed at once to the forging of whatever iron
contrivances might be needed.